<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Hartford assises, March 14. 1616 by John Squire ...</title>
            <author>Squire, John, ca. 1588-1653.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12809</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23116</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1729</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">21507082</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 21507082</idno>
            <idno type="VID">24701</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12809)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 24701)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1716:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Hartford assises, March 14. 1616 by John Squire ...</title>
                  <author>Squire, John, ca. 1588-1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 21 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.S. for Nicholas Bourne, and are to be sould at his shop at the south-entrance of the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]⁴(-A1) B-C⁴ D².</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Exodus XX, 16 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:24701:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24701:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED at Hartford Aſſiſes, <hi>March</hi> 14. 1616.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>John Squire,</hi> Preacher of Gods word in SHOREDITCH.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Nicholas Bourne,</hi> and are to be ſould at his ſhop at the South-entrance of the Royall Exchange. 1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:24701:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24701:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT</hi> WORSHIPFVLL <hi>THOMAS NEWCE, Eſquire, High-Sheriffe of the Countie of HARTFORD; Grace, Mercie, and Peace.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SYR:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O <hi>excuſe</hi> my ſelfe for wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, is the <hi>excuſe</hi> of all Writers: You know it, I omit it. This Sermon was lately preached before you, now printed for you: your intreaty had the one, your command hath the other. Such as it is: it was in the <hi>Eares</hi> of ſome, ſhall be in the <hi>Eyes</hi> of others, and God grant it may be in the <hi>Hearts</hi> of all.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours in the Lord</hi> Iohn Squire.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:24701:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24701:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED AT HARTFORD Aſſiſes, <hi>March.</hi> 14. 1616.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Being vnknowne in this place, and vnexpected of this people, ye may ſpeake that phraſe to mee, which the <hi>King</hi> did to his <hi>Gueſt, Matth.</hi> 22. 12. <hi>Friend how commest thou hither?</hi> I anſwere: I come not from the <hi>South,</hi> as the Queene of <hi>Saba</hi> did, 1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 10. to behold the maieſty of your Country, and admire the magnificence of your companie: Nor come I from the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> as the <hi>wiſe men</hi> did, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2. 11. to <hi>preſent</hi> you with <hi>gold,</hi> and to bring you <hi>golden preſents:</hi> Neither come I from the <hi>Weſt,</hi> as the <hi>violent winde</hi> did, <hi>Exod.</hi> 10. 19. to blow away the <hi>contentious graſſe-hoppers</hi> of this corrupt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: (It muſt be <hi>Virga reformantis,</hi> not <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum informantis,</hi> the <hi>ſword</hi> of the potent Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, not the <hi>word</hi> of the poore Miniſter, which
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:24701:4"/> muſt bring that noble act to paſſe.) But I come from whence <hi>promotion</hi> commeth, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 75. 6. <hi>Neither from the Eaſt, nor from the Weſt, nor from the South; but from the Lord.</hi> From the <hi>Lord</hi> I <hi>come</hi> to you, as one of the children of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets did to the Seſſions of Iſraell, 2 <hi>Reg.</hi> 9. 5. <hi>I come to bring you a meſſage;</hi> Therefore, <hi>harken to me you men of Iſraell, that God may hearken vnto you.</hi> I bring you a <hi>meſſage</hi> from the <hi>Lord:</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> make it honourable vnto him, and profitable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you.</p>
            <p>My <hi>meſſage</hi> which I bring to you, is part of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> his <hi>meſſage</hi> which he brought from <hi>Sinai</hi> to the people of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> as it is written in the 20. chapter of <hi>Exodus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Exod. 20. verſ. 16. <hi>Thou ſhalt not beare falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Text.</note> 
               <hi>againſt thy Neighbor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Would wee be perfect Chriſtians? Then muſt we performe two workes of Chriſtianity: our duty to <hi>God,</hi> and our duty towards <hi>Man.</hi> Our breaches of the laſt may be called <hi>Legion,</hi> for <hi>they are many:</hi> of many, there are two maine ones. Wee wrong our neighbour eyther by the <hi>Violence</hi> of the <hi>hand,</hi> or by the <hi>Virulence</hi> of the <hi>tongue:</hi> The firſt is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited in the precepts praemiſed, the other is forbidden in the Text: the Text therefore doth teach vs, as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaketh. 3 8. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to bridle an vnbridled euill, <hi>to take heede that wee offend not with our tongue: and</hi> wee are bound to obey this precept, by foure
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:24701:4"/> neceſſary bonds: <hi>Diuine, Morall, Naturall, Ciuill. Diuinitie</hi> doth teach that God is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that <hi>God himſelfe, is the truth it ſelfe;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to ſpeake and doe the <hi>truth,</hi> is to burniſh the blemiſhed image, and to ingraue the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the diuinitie in a Chriſtian ſoule: <hi>Our Manners</hi> wee ſenceably apprenend inclining to <hi>falſe-hood, euery man is a lyar,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 4. Therefore muſt this inclination be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, by imbracing the <hi>truth. Nature</hi> looketh vpon an vntruth, as vpon ſome vnnaturall mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: for <hi>Oratio,</hi> is <hi>oris ratio;</hi> the <hi>Soule</hi> is the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and the <hi>Tongue</hi> ſhould be the <hi>Midwife</hi> of <hi>Truth:</hi> Now for the ſoule to <hi>conceiue</hi> a <hi>truth,</hi> and the tongue to <hi>bring</hi> forth a <hi>lye,</hi> this is <hi>vnreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly vnnaturall.</hi> And for <hi>Policie</hi> wee cannot but know, that it is the diſroynting of the body of the common-wealth, if that contracts be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouched by teſtimonies, and if <hi>euery truth be not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed by the mouth of two or three witneſſes.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold then the <hi>neceſsity</hi> obliging vs to the <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>Vae mihi ſi non euangelizauero:</hi> Woe be to me, if I ſpeake it not: Woe be to you if you heare it not; and woe be to vs all, if we practiſe it not: <hi>A neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity is laid vpon vs. Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe againſt thy neighbour,</hi> ſaith my Text.</p>
            <p>I diuide my Text as <hi>Iacob</hi> did his company, <hi>Gen.</hi> 33. 2. into three parts: The <hi>perſon offending, Thou:</hi> The <hi>perſon offended, thy Neighbour:</hi> and the <hi>offence</hi> it ſelfe, <hi>Bearing falſe-witneſſe.</hi> I will inuert the order, and put the <hi>perſons offending hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:24701:5"/> as <hi>Iacob did Rachell and her children,</hi> leſt ſome rough <hi>Eſau</hi> (before he be appeaſed) ſhould be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry and ſmite them, or me for them. I begin with the <hi>Offence, Bearing falſe witneſſe:</hi> Men doe <hi>beare falſe witneſſe</hi> two waies: <hi>Priuately,</hi> and <hi>Publikely<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Priuately,</hi> by our ſelues. <hi>Publikely,</hi> before the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Priuate bearing falſe witneſſe,</hi> is a <hi>body</hi> of ſinne, which I diuide into fiue <hi>members:</hi>
            </p>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Slandering.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Railing.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Tale-bearing.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Flattery.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Lying.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>I may terme theſe fiue ſinnes, the <hi>fiue fingers of Sathan;</hi> for whoſoeuer is tainted with them, vndoubtedly the <hi>Diuell hath a great hand ouer him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Slandering</hi> is both <hi>actiue and paſsiue: Actiue,</hi> when men are <hi>reprouers</hi> of their neighbours by <hi>ſlaunders. Paſsiue,</hi> when they are <hi>approuers</hi> of the <hi>ſlanderers,</hi> by hearing them. Both are forbidden in this Text; for the originall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>gnanah,</hi> ſignifieth both to <hi>ſpeake,</hi> as it is tranſlated in the Text, and to <hi>heare, Pſalme</hi> 143. 1. and both are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed in the 15. <hi>Pſalm. Verſ:</hi> 3. that man ſhal dwell with the Lord, <hi>who ſlaundereth not with his tongue, nor receiueth a falſe report againſt his neighbour.</hi> Whence <hi>Bernard</hi> ſhaped his ſentence, <hi>Non eſſent qui detraherent, ſi non adeſſent qui audirent:</hi> that is, where there are no <hi>Receiuers,</hi> there no <hi>Theeues</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:24701:5"/> will be: and ſtop thou the <hi>eare</hi> of thine owne <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,</hi> do not <hi>heare</hi> ſlanders, and thou ſhalt muzle the <hi>mouth</hi> of <hi>detraction;</hi> few will dare to <hi>ſpeake</hi> ſlanders. And reaſon haue we to performe it: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Diuell</hi> is the <hi>grand-ſlanderer,</hi> the <hi>father</hi> of <hi>ſlanderers,</hi> the <hi>grand-father</hi> of <hi>ſlanderers:</hi> he is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>an accuſer, a ſlanderer:</hi> whence it is well ſaid, if two men be (in communication) one <hi>ſpeaking,</hi> and the other <hi>hearing ſlanders,</hi> they are both <hi>poſſeſſed;</hi> the diuell is in the <hi>eare</hi> of the one, and in the <hi>tongue</hi> of the other. And indeed it is my hearty vnfeigned wiſh, that both the <hi>Speakers</hi> and <hi>Hearers</hi> of <hi>ſlanders,</hi> might be <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Coſbi,</hi> that both might be ſmote through with one ſword of the Magiſtrate at one ſeaſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſecond ſinne is <hi>Railing: Railers</hi> are <hi>open</hi> as <hi>Slaunderers</hi> are <hi>ſecret</hi> aduerſaries of mens repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: the one <hi>vnderminers,</hi> the other <hi>aſſailers</hi> of thy good name: He a <hi>ziba,</hi> this a <hi>Shemei. Railing,</hi> or (as the Scripture phraſe is) <hi>Blaſphemy, Leuit.</hi> 24. 11. is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Killel,</hi> of <hi>Kalel, perforare, to ſtabbe</hi> or <hi>ſmite through,</hi> anſwerable to the phraſe of the pſalmiſt, who ſtileth <hi>words, ſwords;</hi> imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Railers ſtab</hi> at the very <hi>life</hi> of our credit. Happy were we, had we an <hi>Abiſhai,</hi> a Magiſtrate, who would and could take away the <hi>heads of theſe dead dogges;</hi> that <hi>Railers</hi> might no more <hi>barke</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>honeſt</hi> name of their honeſt neighbours.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Tale-bearing</hi> is the next: <hi>Tale-bearers</hi> tell (though) the <hi>truth</hi> (yet) <hi>vntruly</hi> or <hi>vntimely:</hi> and therefore are in <hi>truth, falſe-witneſſes. Leuit.</hi> 19. 16.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:24701:6"/> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not walke about with tales amongst my people:</hi> This was a Law in <hi>Iſraell,</hi> would God it were ſo in <hi>England</hi> alſo. <hi>S. Paul</hi> doth point at theſe men, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 33. they are ſaith hee, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>neuer buſie</hi> at home, <hi>euer buſie, ouer-buſie</hi> abroad. Such are like <hi>Sampſons Foxes, they carry fire with their tailes,</hi> to ſet the whole world in a combuſtion. Oh that wee Engliſh, could deale with theſe <hi>Foxes,</hi> as the <hi>Welſh</hi> men did with their <hi>Wolues!</hi> that wee could plucke off their <hi>skinnes,</hi> till they were extinct, and not one left in a whole nation.</p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Flattery</hi> is the fourth: <hi>Slanderers, Railers, and Tale-bearers, Beare falſe-witneſſe to thee againſt others: Flatterers, beare falſe-witneſſe to thee againſt thy ſelfe.</hi> Therefore doe thou as God doth, <hi>hate them. Pſal.</hi> 12. 3. God threateneth to <hi>cut off flattering lippes:</hi> Theſe are mercenary wretches. <hi>Flatterers</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate themſelues, thereby to ſucke out priuate ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage. As <hi>Iehonadab,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. did proſtitute his ſeruice, to be the <hi>ſhameleſſe</hi> inſtrument of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons ſhamefull</hi> luſt, that ſo hee might inſinuate himſelfe into the fauour of the yong <hi>Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are like <hi>falſe Looking-glaſses,</hi> they make men to appeare to themſelues to be <hi>younger, fairer, and comelier,</hi> then indeed they are: and they haue one true property of <hi>falſe Looking-glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Flatterers hurt our Eyes,</hi> that wee <hi>cannot ſee our ſelues.</hi> If my ſentence might ſtand, I would cenſure ſuch vnto the doome of <hi>Adonibezecke, Iudges</hi> 1. 7. Their <hi>toes</hi> ſhould bee <hi>cut off,</hi> that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:24701:6"/> they might goe to none: their <hi>hands</hi> ſhould be <hi>cut off,</hi> that they might <hi>lay hould</hi> of none: and they ſhould <hi>gather their crummes vnder mens tables:</hi> they fawne like <hi>dogges,</hi> let them feede like <hi>dogges: Flattery</hi> is a worke meriting ſuch a wages.</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Lying</hi> is the laſt limme of the Diuell: This di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelliſh vice hath beene abhorred by all good men at all times. <hi>Cyprian</hi> in his Treatiſe againſt <hi>Game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> doth build his inuection againſt <hi>Dicers,</hi> vpon <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Aleatoribus pag.</hi> 532.</note> this ground: becauſe <hi>gaming</hi> did occaſion <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dram medaciorum,</hi> a world of <hi>lyes. Lactantius</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epit. c.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>all lyes</hi> impious, becauſe (ſaith hee) <hi>eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry lye, aut nocet, aut fallit,</hi> doth eyther <hi>hurt</hi> vs, or <hi>deceiue</hi> vs. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> doth retract, euen <hi>Ironies,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Retract. l.</hi> 1. 6. 1.</note> Rhetoricall figures, onely becauſe they had the <hi>appearance</hi> of <hi>lying:</hi> it repented him of the petty <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Confeſ. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>excuſes</hi> which hee made to his Parents being a childe, and to his Schoole maſter being a boy: and in his Epiſtle to <hi>Vincentius</hi> hee calleth <hi>Truth,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſ.</hi> 48. <hi>Vincen.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the Character</hi> of a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and ſaith, that a holy man <hi>dare not tell a lye.</hi> And doubtleſſe all theſe holy men curſed this ſinne out of the mouth of the holy one of Iſraell, <hi>lying lips are an abomination to the Lord,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon, Prou.</hi> 12. 22. And moſt iuſtlie, for this is the <hi>Ieroboam</hi> that made <hi>Iſraell to ſinne;</hi> all priuate and publicke breaches of this precept, iſſue from this fountaine, <hi>Lying.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bleſſed were that Common-wealth, which would make this common vice like <hi>Ahab,</hi> lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing not one <hi>lyer to piſſe againſt the wall:</hi> and his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:24701:7"/> yoke-fellow <hi>Aequiuocation,</hi> like <hi>Iezabell, breaking the necke of that ſinne,</hi> though the <hi>face</hi> thereof be <hi>painted,</hi> and an impious vice, cloaked with many godly pretences.</p>
            <p>Theſe are <hi>Priuate falſe witneſſes,</hi> but the <hi>Publicke</hi> is the principall <hi>offendour</hi> againſt this precept: Of him more fully in the end of this exerciſe: Heere onely take notice that the <hi>falſe-witneſſe,</hi> will not goe to hell alone, but hath manie attendants. There are ſixe <hi>acceſſories</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto this <hi>Principall:</hi> three before the act, and after the act there are three guiltie of <hi>Bearing falſe witneſſe.</hi> Before <hi>falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> is giuen, men may be acceſſaries thereunto <hi>praecipiendo perſuadendo, &amp; conſulendo,</hi> that is, by <hi>commanding, perſwading,</hi> and by <hi>councelling</hi> any to <hi>beare falſe witneſſe.</hi> Firſt, by <hi>commanding,</hi> eyther <hi>directly,</hi> as 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 9. <hi>Nathan</hi> told <hi>Dauid</hi> that he had <hi>killed Vriah,</hi> when as hee onely <hi>commanded Ioab</hi> to kill him: otherwiſe <hi>indirectly,</hi> when the ſuperiour doth <hi>authorize</hi> inferiours, who are cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, <hi>Prou,</hi> 26. 8. <hi>As a man that putteth a ſtone in a ſling, ſo is hee that giueth authority to a foole.</hi> If I put a <hi>ſtone</hi> into the <hi>ſling</hi> of one, intending to braine his neighbour, I am guilty of that murder: ſo the Magiſtrate authorizing a corrupt man, hee is au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of that corruption. Next, to <hi>perſwade</hi> any vnto <hi>falſe-hood,</hi> is a communicating of that crime, eſpecially by that reall perſwaſion, <hi>Bribery;</hi> ſo <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 12. did the <hi>Iewes giue large Money</hi> to the ſouldiers to teſtifie falſely againſt the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Sauiour. And by <hi>Councelling</hi> men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:24701:7"/> the ſame guilt, as did the ſame <hi>Iewes</hi> in the ſame place, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 15. who <hi>taught</hi> the ſouldiers how to anſwere the Magiſtrates interrogatories. Thus by <hi>commanding, directly</hi> or <hi>indirectly,</hi> by <hi>perſwading,</hi> or by <hi>councelling,</hi> many men be <hi>acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary</hi> vnto <hi>falſe-witneſſe, before</hi> the teſtimony may be tendred. <hi>Afterwards</hi> they may be <hi>acceſſary,</hi> as many waies: <hi>Conniuendo, conſentiendo, defendendo,</hi> that is, by <hi>Conniuence,</hi> or winking at it; by <hi>conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> &amp; approuing it; by <hi>defending</hi> and excuſing it. Thoſe that <hi>winke</hi> at faults are faultie themſelues; This was <hi>Elies</hi> caſe in another cauſe, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3. 13. <hi>becauſe his ſons ran into a ſlander, and hee ſtaid them not,</hi> therefore the hand of the Lord was heauy vpon him. So the Magiſtrate, who doth but ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect <hi>falſe-witneſſe,</hi> or any <hi>falſe-hood,</hi> let him looke <hi>forward</hi> to preuent it, otherwiſe <hi>conniuence</hi> may make him fall <hi>backward; Eli</hi> is a dreadfull exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. <hi>Conſent</hi> alſo contracteth the guilt, be it either <hi>expreſſed</hi> by plaine partaking with impietie, as <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 50. 18. or be it <hi>ſuppreſſed,</hi> as <hi>Prouerb.</hi> 24. 11. 12. <hi>Deliuer them that are drawne to death: if thou ſayeſt, wee know not of it, ſhall not hee that pondereth the heart vnderſtand it?</hi> Not onely tendring, but alſo not hindring of <hi>falſe-witneſſe</hi> is a breach of this commandement. Finally, <hi>excuſe</hi> the <hi>act,</hi> and thou thy ſelfe doeſt <hi>act</hi> the ſinne which thou <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeſt,</hi> for <hi>woe be vnto them which ſpeake good of euill, and euill of good, Iſay</hi> 5. 20. Conclude we then that <hi>Conniuence, conſent</hi> or <hi>defence,</hi> make men <hi>acceſſary</hi> to <hi>falſe-witnes,</hi> though performed. By this I haue
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:24701:8"/> opened many maladies, one word containeth one medicine for al of them: that one word in the <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 15. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>To ſpeake and doe the truth.</hi> This <hi>word,</hi> is like the <hi>word</hi> made fleſh, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. 23. <hi>it healeth euery ſickneſſe, and euery diſeaſe among the people.</hi> To <hi>Plaintiſe</hi> and <hi>Defendant,</hi> to <hi>Iudge</hi> and <hi>Iury,</hi> to <hi>Councellour</hi> and <hi>Aduocate,</hi> to <hi>Witneſſe</hi> and to <hi>All, magna eſt veritas &amp; praeualet; Great is the Truth—</hi>and God grant it may <hi>preuaile</hi> with all of them for euermore.</p>
            <p>The <hi>perſon offended</hi> is our <hi>Neighbour:</hi> our <hi>Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour</hi> hath a double ſignification; eyther it is taken <hi>particularly</hi> for an adioyning acquaintance, as <hi>Luk.</hi> 1. 58. <hi>Neighbours</hi> are called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, men who haue their <hi>houſes neere together:</hi> Or it is taken <hi>generally</hi> for <hi>euery</hi> man, as <hi>Luk.</hi> 10. 37. the <hi>Samaritane</hi> is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the wounded mans <hi>neighbour,</hi> each being an vndoubted ſtranger vnto the other. In this Text it is vſed in the ſecond ſence, a <hi>Neighbour,</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying <hi>any</hi> man, as <hi>Math.</hi> 5. 43. our Sauiour doth argue the gloſſe of the Phariſes, as corrupt, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining the word <hi>Neighbour,</hi> to ſignifie a Friend onely.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Doctrine</hi> of which point doth ſpread it ſelfe into two branches. Firſt Chriſtians muſt haue a care and conſcience that <hi>they beare falſe-witneſſe against no man:</hi> not following the phraſe of <hi>Lucilian</hi> in <hi>Lactantius, Homini amico &amp; famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ari mentiri non eſt meum;</hi> It is not (ſaith hee) my guiſe to <hi>lye</hi> vnto my <hi>friend,</hi> nor <hi>beare falſe-witneſſe</hi> againſt my <hi>acquaintance.</hi> But, <hi>Thou ſhalt not beare</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:24701:8"/> 
               <hi>falſe witneſſe againſt thy neighbour;</hi> that is, againſt <hi>no man,</hi> ſaith my Text. Againe, wee muſt yeeld <hi>true witneſſe</hi> vnto all men. Vnlike the <hi>Athenians,</hi> who were wont to <hi>pray</hi> onely for <hi>themſelues,</hi> and for their <hi>neighbours</hi> of <hi>Chios:</hi> ſo for a Chriſtian to giue <hi>true witneſſe</hi> onely to whom hee is enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by Law, or ingaged by nature, this is <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian, vncircumciſed,</hi> and <hi>heatheniſh.</hi> Both theſe Chriſtian duties are confirmed by Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <hi>Math.</hi> 5. 45. <hi>Be ye children of your Father that is in heauen, for hee maketh the Sunne to riſe both on the good and on the euill; and be a true witneſſe vnto thy neighbour;</hi> that is, to euery one vnder the Sun, ſaith my Text.</p>
            <p>Would God that this inſtruction were as <hi>vſuall</hi> as it is <hi>beneficiall.</hi> Behold heere a <hi>Cyno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſura,</hi> a <hi>loade-ſtarre,</hi> to guide our conſcience, in the propoſing and compoſing of all contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies; eſpecially laying the foundation on that ground of religion, <hi>Math.</hi> 22. 39. <hi>Loue thy neighbour as thy ſelfe.</hi> If the Lord would pleaſe to infuſe it into the hearts of all men, that Iudge, Iurie, Sollicitour, Counſellour, Aduocate, Witneſſe, Accuſer, that euery one would eſteeme the <hi>Accuſed</hi> as <hi>himſelfe:</hi> this wou'd make all men to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to be <hi>Peace keepers,</hi> and <hi>peace makers;</hi> to vſe a Conſcience in accuſing his <hi>Neighbour; Thou ſhalt loue thy Neighbour as thy ſelfe:</hi> this is a principle in <hi>Nature,</hi> God giue vs <hi>Grace</hi> to follow it.</p>
            <p>Many <hi>perſons offending</hi> are compriſed in the firſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:24701:9"/> word, <hi>Thou: Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witnes againſt thy neighbour.</hi> Here the hearer may preach to the Preacher, and ſay to mee, <hi>Phyſitian cure thy ſelfe;</hi> and doe not <hi>Thou beare falſe-witneſſe.</hi> For <hi>falſe-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſtin. Retr.</hi> 224.</note> 
               <hi>wee doe beare,</hi> when wee make our Sermons like the <hi>Manna</hi> (in the Iewiſh fable) to giue a ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall taſte, anſwerable to each ſeuerall appetite: Such <hi>humorous humouring</hi> Sermons, the Lord doth execrate out of the mouth of <hi>Ieremy,</hi> 6. 14. <hi>They haue healed the hurt of my people with ſweet words:</hi> And how they <hi>healed</hi> that <hi>hurt, Cyprian</hi> doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cypr de Lapſis ſect.</hi> 12.</note> by an excellent compariſon: Soothing Preachers are like <hi>vnskilfull Chirurgians,</hi> who ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touch the wound on the <hi>out-ſide,</hi> thereby ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it to feſter the more dangerouſly in the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide.</hi> A fit reſemblance: Who obſcrueth not that the ſmooth tongue of the Preacher, maketh an impoſtumed hart of the hearer? Senſible of which ſinne was holy <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> when he cried to God to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. Conf.</hi> 6. 6.</note> pardon the ſinnes of his youth, but eſpecially this; that being young hee did Preach, <hi>non vt doceret, ſed vt placeret:</hi> to <hi>delight</hi> the eare, rather then to <hi>ſmite</hi> the <hi>heart</hi> of the congregation. Let me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore begin this point with the words of that holy man, being an auncient and penitent Preacher: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. de Vir. Relig. cap.</hi> 55.</note> 
               <hi>Hortor itaque vos omnes chariſsimi, meque ipſum hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor vobiſcum:</hi> I exhort you, firſt framing the ſame exhortation to my ſelfe! <hi>O my ſoule, doe not Thou beare falſe-witneſse:</hi> Be <hi>thou like S. Paul, Epheſ.</hi> 6. 20. <hi>ſpeake thy meſſage boldly, yet ſpeake as thou oughteſt to ſpeake.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:24701:9"/>
            <p> Firſt therefore, the honorable <hi>Iudges</hi> are hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> to be intreated for <hi>Gods cauſe,</hi> that they will <hi>beare true witneſſe</hi> in <hi>Mans cauſe.</hi> I acknowledge my ſelfe an vnworthy inſtructer of them, and their calling: to them therefore I Preach not, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound a Preacher anſwerable to their place; a <hi>Prince,</hi> Preaching vnto <hi>Iudges,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19. 6. &amp; 7. <hi>Take heed what ye doe; for ye execute not the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of man, but of the Lord. Take heed, for with the Lord there is neyther reſpect of perſons, nor receiuing of rewards. Verbum ſapienti,</hi> an excellent Sermon in two words: <hi>There muſt be neyther reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, nor receiuing of rewards.</hi> This is <hi>Iehoſhaphats</hi> Sermon: I doe onely (this day) rehearſe it to your <hi>eares,</hi> the Lord repeate it euery day vnto your <hi>hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neuertheleſſe, although <hi>Eliſha</hi> be good, yet <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> may <hi>Gehazi</hi> be bad: <hi>Naaman</hi> ſueth to be cured of his <hi>leproſie</hi> (to haue ſome controuerſie ended) which hath ſtucke to him, and his, for a long ſeaſon; Noble <hi>Eliſha</hi> biddeth him to waſh in <hi>Iordan,</hi> informeth him in the honeſt eaſie meanes to heale him: onely <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Gehazi</hi> muſt haue a <hi>tallent of ſiluer;</hi> ſome ſiluer, Memorandum, for <hi>admiſsion,</hi> or for <hi>expedition,</hi> A certaine fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low had one <hi>ſquinte eye,</hi> and the other <hi>ſmote out:</hi> here-hence, one ſaid vnto him, thou haſt <hi>two eyes,</hi> but <hi>Vnum ncquam, alterum nequaquam,</hi> with <hi>one eye</hi> thou doeſt <hi>ſee ill,</hi> with the other thou doeſt not <hi>ſee at all.</hi> Hiſtorians ſay that ſome Magiſtrates haue beene attended by ſome ſuch
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:24701:10"/> ſeruants. The Client commeth to <hi>one</hi> ſeruant, hee is <hi>nequaquam,</hi> he <hi>cannot ſee</hi> to helpe him: hee craueth fauour from <hi>another,</hi> and he is <hi>nequam,</hi> hee <hi>will not ſee</hi> to admit him—vnleſſe it be through a <hi>paire of ſiluer ſpectacles.</hi> Theſe are <hi>Gehazies!</hi> O that it were in my power to bequeath them the bleſſing of <hi>Eliſhai!</hi> That <hi>Seruant</hi> to a <hi>Iudge,</hi> that <hi>Clerke</hi> to a <hi>Iustice,</hi> or that <hi>Deputie</hi> to a <hi>Sheriffe,</hi> who ſhall <hi>(be a falſe witneſſe)</hi> ſell his neighbours cauſe, and his Maiſters credit, for a reward, let the <hi>Leproſie</hi> of <hi>Gehazi</hi> cleaue to him for euer: Would God the worme of conſcience might ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ceaſe gnawing their guilty ſoules, till they haue made <hi>ſpeedy reſtitution, and open confeſsion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The great wheele in this Clocke of wickednes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> is the <hi>Plaintife,</hi> or <hi>Accuſer:</hi> Who (though his cauſe be good, yet) if hee proſecute it for <hi>hatred,</hi> like <hi>Doeg,</hi> or for <hi>couetouſneſſe,</hi> like <hi>Iezabell,</hi> then dare I bouldly ſay to ſuch a man, <hi>Thou doſt beare falſe-witneſſe againſt thy neighbour.</hi> But the <hi>Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander,</hi> who loueth to liue in the fire of conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, hee is a <hi>falſe-witneſſe</hi> in an high degree. As <hi>Ferdinando Lopez</hi> aduiſeth ambitious Princes to warre eight or ten yeares with one neighbour; then to picke a quarrell with another, leſt vſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the former to be as cunning as himſelfe: Such a politician is many a <hi>Plaintife,</hi> who doth force his quiet neighbour into a forced vnquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, by turnes, to arme himſelfe for the wicked warre of continuall contention. In this cauſe my prayer in <hi>generall,</hi> is, that the Magiſtrates might
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:24701:10"/> be like the <hi>Aramites,</hi> 1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 22. 34. that they would bend the whole force of iuſtice againſt (this <hi>Ahab)</hi> this man, <hi>who troubleth all Iſraell:</hi> And in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar my vnfeigned prayer is, that heauen would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able my vnworthy ſelfe to be that <hi>Archer,</hi> 1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 22. 34. that <hi>ignorantly</hi> I might ſmite ſome ſuch quarrelling wretch, though hee haue his <hi>harneſſe</hi> on, and commeth with a <hi>ſeared conſcience</hi> to this congregation.</p>
            <p>Theſe haue two maine aſſiſtants: the <hi>Suppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> and the <hi>Reporters</hi> of their cauſe: <hi>Councellours</hi> who ſpeake <hi>to</hi> them in <hi>priuate,</hi> and <hi>Aduocates</hi> who plead <hi>for</hi> them in <hi>publike.</hi> I honour the Law, and will inſtruct them concerning their ſoules, as from my ſoule I deſire they ſhould inſtruct mee concerning my <hi>eſtate:</hi> where I ſuſpect an <hi>ill caſe,</hi> I will <hi>tell it plainely.</hi> Let that imputation laid vpon the <hi>Romiſh Lawyers,</hi> bee as farre from ours, as <hi>Rome</hi> is from <hi>England.</hi> Thus wrote <hi>Hildebert</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Mentz,</hi> of the <hi>Romane court:</hi> imploy them in your cauſes, and they delay them: imploy them not, and they hinder them. If you ſolicite them, they ſcorne you: if you enrich them they forget you. Neuer may this language of <hi>Canaan</hi> be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood in our land of <hi>Iſraell.</hi> Rather what <hi>Poſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donius</hi> reporteth of <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> let that be reported of all good Lawyers: hee would rather <hi>looſe his friend;</hi> and in the name of God, let theſe rather <hi>looſe their fee,</hi> than <hi>conceale the truth.</hi> And let euery conſcionable Lawyer know, that if he aduiſe <hi>in a bad cauſe,</hi> at Gods barre that ſame <hi>Client</hi> ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:24701:11"/> him to be <hi>Eue,</hi> that he gaue the <hi>apple,</hi> that his councel opened the way to the <hi>forbidden fruit:</hi> and as a praeamble to Gods hate, hee ſhall firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre mans hate, <hi>he that ſaith to the wicked, thou art righteous, him ſhall that people curſe, Prou.</hi> 24. 24. Wherefore let me once <hi>councell the Councellor,</hi> of all other: <hi>Doe not thou beare falſe witneſse againſt thy neighbour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neyther can the <hi>conſcience</hi> of the <hi>Aduocate</hi> plead for himſelfe that he is <hi>good,</hi> if his <hi>tongue</hi> doth plead <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> for a cauſe which his conſcience knoweth to bee <hi>bad.</hi> If <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> were not impoſſibilities: Oh that the noble ſoule of <hi>Papinianus</hi> liued in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of our Engliſh <hi>Aduocates.</hi> When <hi>Antoninus</hi> had made away his brother <hi>Geta,</hi> after the firſt yeare of their ioynt Empire, he intreated <hi>Papinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> (a famous Lawyer) to plead his excuſe: Whoſe anſwer was like himſelfe, Noble; It is eaſier ſaid he, <hi>parricidium facere, quam excuſare:</hi> to doe wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly, then to excuſe the wickednes: Thou mayeſt (ſaid hee) command my necke to the Blocke, but not my tongue to the Barre: I prize not my life to the pleading of an ill cauſe. Behold a Pagan man, but a patterne to Chriſtians: and chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity will compell worthy <hi>Aduocates</hi> to imitation: for hee <hi>that iuſtifieth the wicked, and he that condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the iuſt, are both an abhomination to the Lord, Prou.</hi> 17. 15. Therefore as the boy euery day cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto King <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Remember that thou art a man:</hi> So is it my hearty wiſh, that whenſoeuer the <hi>Aduocate</hi> is
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:24701:11"/> beginning to plead, that then the ſpirit of God would whiſper vnto his ſoule, the words of my Text. Take heed, now: <hi>Doe not thou beare falſe witneſſe against thy neighbour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Other acceſſaries vnto <hi>falſe witneſſe,</hi> may be <hi>Bailiffes</hi> and <hi>vnder-Sheriffs.</hi> Some haue beene <hi>ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected,</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> (I would it were a <hi>ſuſpition</hi> onely,) that Writs being ſent into the country, haue beene en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained by theſe officers, as the <hi>Ephramites</hi> were by the <hi>Gileadites, Iudg.</hi> 12. 6. If they cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce <hi>Shibboleth,</hi> but <hi>Sibboleth:</hi> if there be but a ſyllable wanting in the word, but a <hi>quadrine</hi> in the <hi>gratification;</hi> they cannot paſſe, they dye for it, they muſt goe no further. Now theſe men doe hinder <hi>true</hi> witneſſe, and thereby come within the compaſſe of <hi>falſe witneſſe.</hi> And indeed, ſuch as do <hi>hinder the Law from execution,</hi> happy were it, if the Law would put them to <hi>execution.</hi> To euery one of them therefore, let me cry againe, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, as <hi>loud as thunder</hi> (for they dwell neere <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tadupa:</hi> theſe men are very deafe of that eare:) let me I ſay cry againe, and againe, to euery one of them, as <hi>loud as thunder: Doe not thou beare falſe witneſſe againſt thy neighbour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Iurie</hi> alſo may be the inſtruments of <hi>falſe</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 
               <hi>witneſſe.</hi> The <hi>Iurie</hi> ſhould be like the <hi>Diſciples,</hi> Luk. 10. 5. whereſoeuer they come, they ſhould ſay, <hi>peace be to this houſe:</hi> but ſometimes they are like the <hi>Apoſtles, Ioh.</hi> 6. 70. they are <hi>twelue</hi> in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, but one of them is often (too often) a <hi>Diuell,</hi> a diuelliſh <hi>Iudas,</hi> who will betray the cauſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:24701:12"/> the country, and betray the company, for fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy lucre. Would you know him by his badge? hee vſually <hi>beareth the bagge, and Bribery</hi> is his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. I heard of a wretch who ſued that authority might <hi>flicke</hi> him on a Iurie, that ſo hee might <hi>ſticke</hi> to his friend: if the Magiſtrate would <hi>ſticke</hi> ſuch a Pagan, as <hi>Ehud</hi> did <hi>sticke Eglon, Iudg</hi> 3. 21. he had a right recompence of reward. To preuent this vnchriſtian inſolency, iniury, periury, to each of the <hi>Iurie</hi> I muſt propound a new Text, <hi>the third Commandement. Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vaine, for the Lord will not hold him guiltleſse that taketh his name in vaine:</hi> Let the Iurie note onely that one phraſe, if they ſweare and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare, <hi>God will not hold them guiltleſſe.</hi> Let the <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment</hi> of the third precept be their <hi>admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> for the ninth precept: You are to <hi>ſweare by God, and before God;</hi> therefore as you tender an oath, and tremble at Gods wrath, I charge you vpon the perill of your ſoules, let you Verdit ſhun this rocke: <hi>Doe not beare falſe witneſſe againſt thy Neighbour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto haue I <hi>muſter'd</hi> out an army of rebels againſt this precept, yet remaineth the <hi>King</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde: hee is like <hi>Saul,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. 22. hee will <hi>hide himſelfe</hi> as aſhamed of his <hi>dignity:</hi> Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding plucke him out, and you ſhall finde him (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed like <hi>Saul) higher than</hi> all the premiſed offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors <hi>by the ſhoulders vpward.</hi> This <hi>vaſſall</hi> of ſinne, and <hi>veſſell</hi> of Sathan, is named in the expreſſe phraſe of my Text; <hi>A falſe-witneſſe</hi> is this man,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:24701:12"/> this monſter of men, a Knight of the <hi>Post,</hi> who doth <hi>poſt</hi> to perdition: a miſchieuous miſcreant, execrable to all men and narions. <hi>A falſe witneſſe</hi> is dragged to damnation by a threefold gable of wickedneſſe; he is guilty of <hi>breach</hi> of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying a <hi>Lye,</hi> and of (the ſinne of ſinnes) <hi>Periury,</hi> ſaith <hi>Aquinas;</hi> and therefore moſt worthily exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> puniſhed ſuch by a <hi>Tali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, limme</hi> for <hi>limme,</hi> and <hi>life</hi> for <hi>life:</hi> what he intended to <hi>offer</hi> by his falſehood, the ſame was hee iudged to <hi>ſuffer</hi> for his falſehood. The <hi>Romans</hi> cenſured a conuicted <hi>falſe-witneſſe</hi> to be plunged head long <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zanchi. tom.</hi> 4. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 193.</note> from the ſteep mountain <hi>Tarpeia.</hi> Excellent lawes; no fault but this, they are not in force with vs in England. The holie ghoſt doth diſplay this infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell in (yet) more liuely colours. <hi>Pro.</hi> 25. 18 <hi>A falſe witneſſe</hi> is compared to an <hi>Hammer, a ſword and a ſharpe arrow.</hi> Firſt for himſelfe, becauſe he hauing once cracked his credit (and being known for falſe and for ſworne by him that hired him) like to thoſe <hi>iron inſtruments,</hi> he becommeth <hi>hard,</hi> and putteth on a harlots face: ſhameles of <hi>Periurie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer, there are three ſeuerall perſons are ſmote by his falſe tongue, three ſeuerall waies, anſwerably to thoſe three inſtruments: firſt a <hi>falſe witneſſe</hi> is an <hi>Hammer</hi> to the <hi>Iudge,</hi> hee doth aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh him (as if one man ſhould ſmite another in the head with an <hi>hammer,)</hi> ſo that hee knoweth not what to determine. Next he is a <hi>ſword</hi> to him that <hi>hired</hi> him, hee incourageth him with hope to vanquiſh his aduerſary the ſecond time by his
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:24701:13"/> 
               <hi>purſe,</hi> and putteth a <hi>ſword</hi> into his <hi>hand</hi> to <hi>kill</hi> the innocent. Finally hee is a <hi>ſharpe arrow</hi> to him <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom he doth witneſſe,</hi> (though that man be leaſt in damaged, haue he but grace to be patient) yet to him he is a <hi>ſharpe arrow,</hi> to <hi>ſticke</hi> in his life, eſtate, reputation. To conclude: I ſay <hi>of a falſe-witneſſe,</hi> hee is an <hi>Ahab,</hi> a villaine, who hath <hi>ſould himſelfe to worke wickedneſſe in the fight of the Lord:</hi> And I ſay to <hi>a falſe-witneſſe,</hi> as <hi>Simon Peter, did to Simon Magus, Acts</hi> 8. 23. and 22. <hi>Thou art in the gall of bitterneſſe, and in the bond of iniquity, pray vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God,—if ſo be—that the wickedneſſe of bearing falſe witneſſe may be forgiuen thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus haue I ripped vp this excellent Text, and it may be ſome impious conſcience alſo. Wee ſee the diſeaſe, what medicine remaineth to cure it? The ordinary meanes is this: to make the <hi>Sermon,</hi> like the <hi>Preacher.</hi> The <hi>Preacher:</hi> you ſee me to day, I goe away, and moſt of you ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſee me any more: So for the <hi>Sermon,</hi> you haue heard it to day; it goeth away, and many (I am affraid too many) of you will neuer <hi>thinke</hi> on it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. This is the vſuall medicine: not ſo much as to <hi>thinke</hi> on the Sermons which goad our guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty conſcience. But beware, it is deſperate Phyſick, it is <hi>Opium,</hi> it will caſt you into a <hi>dead ſleepe,</hi> that you ſhall drop into <hi>Hell,</hi> before you ſo much as <hi>dreame</hi> of <hi>damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Giue me leaue therefore to preſcribe another: Indeed it is a <hi>Coraſiue,</hi> but <hi>ſoueraigne</hi> notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Let this time tranſport our ſoules to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:24701:13"/> one another time: Now you ſee one <hi>Iudge,</hi> the time will come when we muſt come before a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother: one whom we belieue will come to <hi>Iudge both the quicke and the dead.</hi> As now the trembling malefactor is ledde out with a diſmai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d ſoule, to behold the dreadful aſpect of the ſeuere death-ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencing Magiſtrate: ſo then the <hi>guilty conſcience</hi> ſhall be haled forth by thouſands of miniſtring flames of fire, to appeare before that <hi>Iudge</hi> whoſe face is Maieſty, and frowne confuſion: Doe but thinke vpon this; the very thought of it wil com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell the <hi>Preacher</hi> to <hi>instruct bouldly,</hi> the <hi>Iudge</hi> to <hi>determine iuſtly,</hi> the <hi>Seruant</hi> to <hi>informe honeſtly,</hi> the <hi>Plaintife</hi> to <hi>accuſe vprightly,</hi> the <hi>Counſellor</hi> to <hi>aduiſe wiſely,</hi> the <hi>Aduocate</hi> to <hi>pleade warily,</hi> the <hi>vnder-Officers</hi> to <hi>execute law impartially,</hi> the <hi>Iurie</hi> to giue their <hi>Verdit ſincerely,</hi> the <hi>witneſſe</hi> to <hi>ſweare feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,</hi> and giue <hi>euidence truely:</hi> and <hi>all of vs to liue conſcionably.</hi> We are before one <hi>Iudge,</hi> we ſhall be before another: The <hi>Lord</hi> grant that we may ſo diſcharge our duties <hi>this day,</hi> that we be not afraid to appeare before that Great <hi>Iudge at the laſt day. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:24701:14"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24701:14"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24701:15"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24701:15"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24701:16"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24701:16"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24701:17"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24701:17"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24701:18"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24701:18"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24701:19"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24701:19"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24701:20"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24701:20"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24701:21"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:24701:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
